<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: appearance | Emacs Redux]]></title>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/categories/appearance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-07T11:45:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://emacsredux.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Customizing the Fringes]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2015/01/18/customizing-the-fringes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-18T09:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2015/01/18/customizing-the-fringes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On graphical displays, each Emacs window normally has narrow <strong>fringes</strong> (gutters/margins)
on the left and right edges. The fringes are used to display symbols
that provide information about the text in the window. You can type
<code>M-x fringe-mode</code> to disable the fringes, or modify their width. This
command affects fringes in all frames; to modify fringes on the
selected frame only, use <code>M-x set-fringe-style</code>. You can make your
changes to the fringes permanent by customizing the variable
<code>fringe-mode</code>.</p>

<p>Out-of-the-box the most common use of the fringes is to indicate a continuation
line. When one line of text is split into multiple screen lines, the
left fringe shows a curving arrow for each screen line except the
first, indicating that “this is not the real beginning”. The right
fringe shows a curving arrow for each screen line except the last,
indicating that “this is not the real end”. If the line's direction is
right-to-left, the meanings of the curving
arrows in the fringes are swapped.</p>

<p>Third-party modes like
<a href="https://github.com/flycheck/flycheck">flycheck</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/dgutov/diff-hl">diff-hl</a> also make use of the fringe to
display valuable information there (e.g. lint and VC information).</p>

<p>By default both fringes have width 8 pixels, but we can easily adjust this:</p>

<p>``` cl
;; make both fringes 4 pixels wide
(fringe-mode 4)</p>

<p>;; make the left fringe 4 pixels wide and the right disappear
(fringe-mode '(4 . 0))</p>

<p>;; restore the default sizes
(fringe-mode nil)
```</p>

<p>As mentioned before, you can also invoke this command interactively and
determine the optimal fringe size for you, before making it permanent in
your config. The options presented by the <code>fring-mode</code> command are defined
in the <code>fringe-styles</code> list:</p>

<p>``` cl
(defconst fringe-styles
  '(("default" . nil)</p>

<pre><code>("no-fringes" . 0)
("right-only" . (0 . nil))
("left-only" . (nil . 0))
("half-width" . (4 . 4))
("minimal" . (1 . 1)))
</code></pre>

<p>  "Alist mapping fringe mode names to fringe widths.
Each list element has the form (NAME . WIDTH), where NAME is a
mnemonic fringe mode name and WIDTH is one of the following:
- nil, which means the default width (8 pixels).
- a cons cell (LEFT . RIGHT), where LEFT and RIGHT are
  respectively the left and right fringe widths in pixels, or
  nil (meaning the default width).
- a single integer, which specifies the pixel widths of both
fringes.")
```</p>

<p>Be careful when playing with the fringe size. Certain info doesn't
look very good when the fringe is too small (e.g. less than 4 pixels).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
