<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Editing | Emacs Redux]]></title>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/categories/editing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-30T12:26:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://emacsredux.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Highlight matching delimiters with smartparens]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/11/01/highlight-matching-delimiters-with-smartparens/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T16:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/11/01/highlight-matching-delimiters-with-smartparens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago I wrote about
<a href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/04/01/highlight-matching-parentheses/">highlighting matching parentheses</a>
with <code>show-paren-mode</code>. This is definitely useful, but it's kind of
restrictive, since parentheses are just a specific kind of paired
delimiter. Single and double quotes are also paired delimiters (at
least in most programmming languages). In the Ruby programmming
language, for instance, <code>do</code> and <code>end</code> also constitute paired
delimiter.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Fuco1/smartparens">smartparens</a> offers
extremely customizable handling of paired delimiters and comes with an
extra minor mode called <code>show-smartparens-mode</code> to highlight
them. This mode totally replaces <code>show-paren-mode</code> and language
specific modes like <code>hirb</code> (which highlights Ruby blocks).</p>

<p>Assuming you're already using <code>smartparens</code>, enabling <code>show-smartparens-mode</code> is trivial:</p>

<p><code>cl
(show-smartparens-global-mode +1)
</code></p>

<p>Here's a glimpse of it in action:</p>

<p><img src="/images/articles/show-smartparens-mode.gif"></p>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude">Prelude</a> <code>show-paren-mode</code> was
replaced by <code>show-smartparens-mode</code> some time ago.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open line above]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/06/15/open-line-above/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T09:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/06/15/open-line-above</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post continues a topic that was introduced in
<a href="/blog/2013/03/26/smarter-open-line/">smarter open-line</a> few months
back.</p>

<p>Often when editing code one wishes to open a line just above the
current one, which is properly indented relative to the existing code,
and position the cursor at its beginning.  Such a feature is present
in most IDEs, such as IntelliJ IDEA, Eclipse and NetBeans. It’s
sometimes bound to <code>Control+Shift+Enter</code>. Last time I showed you how
to implement a similar function called <code>smart-open-line</code>, this time
will implement <code>smart-open-line-above</code>. Just add this snippet to your
<code>.emacs</code> (or <code>.emacs.d/init.el</code> or whatever):</p>

<p>``` cl
(defun smart-open-line-above ()
  "Insert an empty line above the current line.
Position the cursor at it's beginning, according to the current mode."
  (interactive)
  (move-beginning-of-line nil)
  (newline-and-indent)
  (forward-line -1)
  (indent-according-to-mode))</p>

<p>(global-set-key [(control shift return)] 'smart-open-line-above)
```</p>

<p>Evaluate the code (or restart Emacs) and you'll be able to use
<code>M-x smart-open-line-above</code> or <code>Control+Shift+Enter</code> (aka <code>C-S-return</code>).</p>

<p>Admittedly this keybinding kind of sucks, so here's another option for
you - <code>M-o</code> (used by default as the prefix for some font setting
commands nobody ever uses) for <code>smart-open-line</code> and <code>M-O</code> for
<code>smart-open-line-above</code>.</p>

<p><code>cl
(global-set-key (kbd "M-o") 'smart-open-line)
(global-set-key (kbd "M-O") 'smart-open-line-above)
</code></p>

<p>Another good option would be to fold the two commands into one and use a
prefix argument to trigger the opening a new line above the current
one.</p>

<p>This command is part of
<a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude">Prelude</a>(it's named
<code>prelude-smart-open-line-above</code> there).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continue a comment on the next line]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/06/05/continue-a-comment-on-the-next-line/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T16:12:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/06/05/continue-a-comment-on-the-next-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When writing code from time to time we have to write comments as
well. Most of the time programmers are using single-line comments,
denoted by some special starting character(s), like <code>#</code>, <code>//</code>,
etc. When you want to write a few lines of comments in Emacs you have two
options:</p>

<h4>Option A</h4>

<ul>
<li>Write the first line of the comment.</li>
<li>Go to the next line.</li>
<li>Insert the comment delimiter.</li>
<li>Continue writing the comment.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Option B (editor's choice)</h4>

<ul>
<li>White the first line of the comment.</li>
<li>Press <code>M-j</code> (<code>indent-new-comment-line</code>).</li>
<li>Continue writing the comment on the second line.</li>
</ul>


<p>The command breaks the line at point and indents the following line,
continuing the comment if invoked within one. The indentation on the
second line matches the indentation on the first line.</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<h1>first line</h1>

<h1>indented line|(we press <code>M-j</code> here)</h1>

<h1>|(we get here after pressing <code>M-j</code>)</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>This command is intended for styles where you write a comment per
line, starting a new comment (and terminating it if necessary) on each
line.  If you want to continue one comment of the type <code>/* */</code> across
several lines, use <code>C-j</code> (<code>newline-and-indent</code>).</p>

<p>Outside of comments <code>M-j</code> behaves pretty much the same way as <code>C-j</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining lines]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/05/30/joining-lines/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T16:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/05/30/joining-lines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Often, while editing, you'll want to compress a few lines into
one. Here's a simple example to illustrate the problem at hand. We
want to convert this bit of Ruby code:</p>

<p>``` ruby
some_method(arg1,</p>

<pre><code>        arg2,
        arg3)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>into:</p>

<p><code>ruby
some_method(arg1, arg2, arg3)
</code></p>

<p>Doing so is extremely easy. Just go to the last line in the first code
block and press 3 times <code>M-^</code> (<code>delete-indentation</code>, aliased
also to <code>join-line</code>).</p>

<p>If you're like me and like to join lines from top to bottom - go to
the first line and press <code>C-u M-^</code> three times. This works, but it is
kind of hard to press <code>C-u M-^</code> repeatedly, compared to just
<code>M-^</code>. Let's simplify this a bit:</p>

<p><code>cl
(defun top-join-line ()
  "Join the current line with the line beneath it."
  (interactive)
  (delete-indentation 1))
</code></p>

<p>Isn't this a top way to join lines or what?</p>

<p>Since <code>delete-indentation</code> is bound both to <code>M-^</code> it makes
sense to use something like <code>C-^</code> for the new command:</p>

<p><code>cl
(global-set-key (kbd "C-^") 'top-join-line)
</code></p>

<p>That's mostly a personal preference I guess - feel free to use any other keycombo.</p>

<p>This command is part of
<a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude">Prelude</a>(it's named
<code>prelude-top-join-line</code> there) and it's bound to <code>C-^</code> there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smarter navigation to the beginning of a line]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/05/22/smarter-navigation-to-the-beginning-of-a-line/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T17:48:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/05/22/smarter-navigation-to-the-beginning-of-a-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Emacs there are two essential commands when you have to go the
beginning of a line - <code>move-beginning-of-line</code>(bound to <code>C-a</code>) and
<code>back-to-indentation</code>(bound to <code>M-m</code>). The first takes you to the
first column of a line and the latter takes you the first non-whitespace
character on a line.</p>

<p>Generally, I find <code>back-to-indentation</code> more useful, but occasionally
it makes sense to go to the real beginning of a line as well. What
doesn't make sense is to have to think all the time what command is
the most appropriate in a particular situation. Wouldn't it be great
if <code>C-a</code> initially took you to the first non-whitespace char(as
<code>back-to-indentation</code> does) on a line, and if pressed again took
you to the actual beginning of the line? It would be! Let's get it
done:</p>

<p>``` cl
(defun smarter-move-beginning-of-line (arg)
  "Move point back to indentation of beginning of line.</p>

<p>Move point to the first non-whitespace character on this line.
If point is already there, move to the beginning of the line.
Effectively toggle between the first non-whitespace character and
the beginning of the line.</p>

<p>If ARG is not nil or 1, move forward ARG - 1 lines first.  If
point reaches the beginning or end of the buffer, stop there."
  (interactive "<sup>p")</sup>
  (setq arg (or arg 1))</p>

<p>  ;; Move lines first
  (when (/= arg 1)</p>

<pre><code>(let ((line-move-visual nil))
  (forward-line (1- arg))))
</code></pre>

<p>  (let ((orig-point (point)))</p>

<pre><code>(back-to-indentation)
(when (= orig-point (point))
  (move-beginning-of-line 1))))
</code></pre>

<p>;; remap C-a to `smarter-move-beginning-of-line'
(global-set-key [remap move-beginning-of-line]</p>

<pre><code>            'smarter-move-beginning-of-line)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The command will keep toggling between the first non-whitespace char
and the beginning of the line when invoked.</p>

<p>Here's a visual example(<code>|</code> is the cursor):</p>

<p>``` bash
This is a short example</p>

<pre><code>text|
# pressing C-a once
</code></pre>

<p>   |text</p>

<pre><code># pressing C-a again
</code></pre>

<p>|   text</p>

<pre><code># pressing C-a again
</code></pre>

<p>   |text
```</p>

<p>This functionality could also be implemented with <code>defadvice</code>, but I tend to avoid their use.</p>

<p><code>smarter-move-beginning-of-line</code> is part of <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude">Prelude</a>.</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> The credit for this tip goes to <a href="https://github.com/lunaryorn">Sebastian Wiesner</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
