<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: macOS | Emacs Redux]]></title>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/categories/macos/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-31T22:52:05+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://emacsredux.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Crazy Productivity Boost: Remapping Return to Control (2017 Edition)]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2017/12/31/a-crazy-productivity-boost-remapping-return-to-control-2017-edition/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-31T11:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2017/12/31/a-crazy-productivity-boost-remapping-return-to-control-2017-edition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2013 I wrote about my favourite productivity boost in Emacs,
namely <a href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/11/12/a-crazy-productivity-boost-remap-return-to-control/">remapping Return to
Control</a>,
which in combination with the classic remapping of <code>CapsLock</code> to
<code>Control</code> makes it really easy to get a grip on Emacs's obsession with
the Control key.</p>

<p>In the original article I suggested to OS X (now macOS) users the tool
<code>KeyRemap4MacBook</code>, which was eventually renamed to
<a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/">Karabiner</a>. Unfortunately this tool
stopped working in macOS Sierra, due to some internal kernel
architecture changes.</p>

<p>That was pretty painful for me as it meant that on my old MacBook
I couldn't upgrade to the newest macOS editions and on my new
MacBook I couldn't type properly in Emacs (as it came with Sierra pre-installed)...
Bummer!</p>

<p>Fortunately 2 years later this is finally solved - the Karabiner team
rewrote Karabiner from scratch for newer macOS releases and recently
added my dream feature to the new <code>Karabiner Elements</code>. Unlike in the
past though, this remapping is not actually bundled with Karabiner by
default, so you have to download and enable it manually from
<a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/complex_modifications/#caps_and_return_to_ctrl">here</a>.</p>

<p>That's actually even better than what I had originally suggested, as
here it's also suggested to use <code>CapsLock</code> with a dual purpose as
well - <code>Control</code> when held down and <code>Escape</code> otherwise.  I have no
idea how this never came to my mind, but it's truly epic! A crazy
productivity boost just got even crazier!</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
