<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linux | Emacs Redux]]></title>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://emacsredux.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-30T12:38:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://emacsredux.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bozhidar Batsov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remap Return to Control in GNU/Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2016/01/30/remap-return-to-control-in-gnu-slash-linux/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-30T11:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://emacsredux.com/blog/2016/01/30/remap-return-to-control-in-gnu-slash-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A long time ago I wrote about
<a href="http://emacsredux.com/blog/2013/11/12/a-crazy-productivity-boost-remap-return-to-control/">remapping Return to Control in OS X</a>.
This was the best productivity boost for my Emacs experience ever!</p>

<p>Recently I've bought a Windows ultrabook (wanted something as light as
MacBook Air, but more powerful and versatile) and I'm doing most of my
work there in a Xubuntu VM. The first thing I did while setting up Xubuntu
was to figure out how to do the aforementioned remapping.</p>

<p>In my original post some people suggested the tool
<a href="https://github.com/alols/xcape">xcape</a>, so I took a look at it.  The
tool can certainly use some documentation improvements (and pre-built
packages), but it gets the job done. After you've installed it you
just need to add the following to your login shell's init file
(e.g. <code>.bash_profile</code>) and you're in business:</p>

<p>```
xmodmap -e "remove Control = Control_R"
xmodmap -e "keycode 0x69 = Return"
xmodmap -e "keycode 0x24 = Control_R"
xmodmap -e "add Control = Control_R"</p>

<p>xcape -t 10000 -e "Control_R=Return"
```</p>

<p>Obviously the first time around you should source <code>.bash_profile</code>
after updating it:</p>

<p><code>
$ . .bash_profile
</code></p>

<p>This is definitely a lot more work than just clicking in the GUI of
the wonderful <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/">Karabiner</a>, but it yields
the desired results and that's what's important at the end of the day.</p>

<p>Now if only there was a way to achieve the same result in Windows...</p>

<p>P.S. <code>vim</code> users will love <code>xcape</code>. Its default behaviour is to
generate the <code>Escape</code> key when <code>Left Control</code> is pressed and released on
its own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
